Vincent Glinsky Papers
Vincent Glinsky Papers
1929-1964
Glinsky, Vincent, 1895-1975
1 linear ft.
Spanning 1929 to 1964, the Vincent Glinsky Papers comprises correspondence, artwork reproductions, writings, and memorabilia of the Russian American sculptor and educator. While illuminating his professional career, the collection also reflects Glinsky's political activities in support of federal aid to the arts and in the interest of world peace.
149006
Biographical History
Vincent Glinsky (1895-1975) was a Russian-American artist and sculptor.
Glinsky was born in Russia on 18 Dec 1895. After coming to America in early childhood, he attended school in Syracuse, New York and then studied at Columbia University's School of Architecture (1924-1925), City College of New York, and the Beaux Arts Institute of Design. In 1935 Glinsky received a Guggenheim Fellowship and soon after left America to settle in Italy and then France. During the Depression Glinsky returned to the United States and worked as a WPA artist and architectural artist.
He has held many one-man shows both in Europe and in the United States. Among the exhibitions he has participated in are the Golden Gate Exposition in San Francisco, the International Watercolor Exhibition in Chicago, and the Contemporary American Art Exhibition in London in 1941.
From 1938-1940 he was the instructor of sculpture at the Beaux Arts Institute of Design in New York. He also taught at Brooklyn College (1949-1955) and in Columbia University's Adult Education Division (summers, 1957-1961).
Glinsky belonged to many clubs and organizations, but his primary interest was in the Audubon Artists and the Architectural League of New York, of which he was vice-president from 1956 to 1958.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
Incoming letters and a few outgoing carbons, together with a variety of printed materials, constitute the Correspondence Subject Files (Box 1). Correspondents include fellow artists (Edmond Amateis, Rudulph Evans, Joseph Konzal, Georg Lober, Oronzio Maldarelli, Jacques Schnier, Adolph Alexander Weinman); authors (Kate S. Heyman, Beatrice Gilman Proske); art patrons and specialists (John Coolidge, Edith Halpert, Archer Milton Huntington); and political figures (Sherman Adams, J. William Fulbright, Hubert H. Humphrey, Eleanor Roosevelt, Henry A. Wallace). Organizational correspondence includes that of educational institutions (Beaux Arts Institute of Design, Columbia University, New York University); museums (Carnegie Institute, Metropolitan Museum of Art, Pennsylvania Academy of the Fine Arts, Whitney Museum of American Art); patrons (National Safety Council, U. S. Treasury Department); political affiliations (American Continental Congress for World Peace, National Council of American Soviet Friendship, Inc., Russian War Relief, Inc., World Congress for Peace); and professional associations (American Academy of Arts and Letters, Architectural League of New York, Audubon Artists, Inc., National Academy of Design, National Sculpture Society).
Artwork consists of periodical reproductions and a photograph, while an article which appeared in the National Sculpture Review, written in collaboration with Glinsky's wife, sculptor Cleo Hartwig, is the sole item in Writings.
Memorabilia (Boxes 1-3) encompasses articles and clippings (1929-1964) about Glinsky, as well as a number of exhibition catalogs ranging from the 1920s through the 1960s.
Subject and Genre Headings
Art -- Sculptors; Glinsky, Vincent, 1895-1975.; Art, American -- 20th century.; Artists -- United States.; Russian Americans.; Sculptors -- United States.; Sculpture, American -- 20th century.; Articles.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Exhibition catalogs.; Pamphlets.; Artists.; Sculptors.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Vincent Glinsky, 1964, 1965.
Inventory
- Correspondence-Subject Files
  - Adams, Sherman, 1958 (Box 1)
  - Amateis, Edmond, 1947 (Box 1)
  - American Academy of Arts and Letters, 1945 (Box 1)
  - American Continental Congress for World Peace, 1949 (Box 1)
  - Architectural League of New York, 1946-1963 (Box 1)
  - Audubon Artists, Inc., 1944-1946; 1963 (Box 1)
  - Beaux Arts Institute of Design, 1932-1942 (Box 1)
  - Carnegie Institute, 1940-1941 (Box 1)
  - Columbia University, 1957-1960 (Box 1)
  - Coolidge, John, 1961-1962 (Box 1)
  - Evans, Rudulph, 1956 (Box 1)
  - Fairmount Park Art Association, 1940; 1949 (Box 1)
  - Fulbright, J. William, 1954 (Box 1)
  - Halpert, Edith, 1949 (Box 1)
  - Heyman, Kate Selma, 1939 (Box 1)
  - Humphrey, Hubert H., 1959 (Box 1)
  - Huntington, Archer Milton, 1946-1948 (Box 1)
  - Konzal, Joseph, 1956 (Box 1)
  - Lober, Georg, 1947 (Box 1)
  - Maldarelli, Oronzio, undated (Box 1)
  - Metropolitan Museum of Art (New York, N.Y.), 1942; 1960 (Box 1)
  - National Academy of Design, 1946-1952 (Box 1)
  - National Arts Club, 1958 (Box 1)
  - National Council of American Soviet Friendship, Inc., 1946-1950 (Box 1)
  - National Safety Council, 1956 (Box 1)
  - National Sculpture Society, 1942-1960; undated (Box 1)
  - New York University, 1952-1963 (Box 1)
  - Pennsylvania Academy of the Fine Arts, 1946-1960 (Box 1)
  - Philadelphia Art Alliance, 1936; 1948-1949 (Box 1)
  - Proske, Beatrice Gilman, 1952 (Box 1)
  - Rivera, Diego, See American Continental Congress for World Peace
  - Roosevelt, Eleanor, 1946 (Box 1)
  - Russian War Relief, Inc., 1942 (Box 1)
  - Schnier, Jacques, 1948 (Box 1)
  - United States. Treasury Department, 1937-1939; undated (Box 1)
  - Wallace, Henry A., 1946 (Box 1)
  - Weinman, Adolph Alexander, 1946 (Box 1)
  - Western Printing and Lithographing Company, 1961 (Box 1)
  - Whitney Museum of American Art, 1946-1954 (Box 1)
  - World Congress for Peace, 1949 (Box 1)
  - A-Z, 1 folder (Box 1)
- Artwork
  - Reproductions (by title), A-Z (Box 1)
- Writings
  - "Direct Carving in Stone", 1965; Article, National Sculpture Review Summer 1965 (Box 1)
- Memorabilia
  - Articles about, 1929-1962; undated; 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Clippings, 1929-1964 (Box 2)
  - Exhibition catalogs, 1920s-1960s; undated; 7 folders (Box 2)